03_UnitTestingAndIsolation



Testing 

	- Testing is an important part of the application lifecycle

		- In our ever-changing environment, testing is necessity 

		- New features need to be verified, before delivered to the client

	- Testing is a wide area of application developement

		- There are several levels of testing

		- There are different types of testing



Unit Testing 

	- A level of software testing where individual components are tested

		- The purpose is to validate that each unit performs as designed

	- The lowest level of software testing

	- Normally performed by software developers themselves

	- Often neglected, but it is in fact, the most important level of testing

	- Unit Testing is often isolated in order to ensure individual testing

		- Testing frameworks often provide mocking functionality




Mocking

	- Mocking - something made as an imitation

	- Mocking is a software practice, primarily used in Unit Testing

		- An object under testing may have dependencies on other objects

		- To isolate the behavior, the other objects are replaced

			- The replacements are mocked objects

			- The mocked objects simulate the behavior of the real objects

	- Basically, Mocking is creating objects that simulate behavior



Unit Testing Benefits

	- Unit testing increases confidence in changing/maintaining code 

	- Developement is faster:

		- Verifying the correctness of new functionality is not manual

		- Localizing bugs, introduced in developement is much faster

	- Debugging is easy:

		- When a test fails, only the latest changes need to be checked





Unit Testing a Web Application

	- Unit testing web apps is pretty much like casial unit testing

	- Writing test mehtods to test classes and methods(functionalities)

		- Testing individual code components (units)

		- Independently from the infrastructure

	- When using a web frameworks such as Spring MVC

		- Build-in logic does not need to be tested
	
		- You still need to test your custom functionality




Testing a simple service with mocking in an Spring MVC app


=======================================================================================
public class UserServiceTests {
	private User testUser;
	private UserRepository mockedUserRepository;

	@Beforepublic void init() {
		this.testUser = new User() {{ 
			setId("SOME_UUID"); 
			setUsername("Pesho"); 
			setPassword("123"); }};
	
	this.mockedUserRepository = Mockito.mock(UserRepository.class);
	}

	@Test
	public void userService_GetUserWithCorrectUsername_ShouldReturnCorrect() {
	
	// Arrange
	Mockito.when(this.mockedUserRepository.findByUsername("Pesho"))
		.thenReturn(this.testUser);
	UserService userService = new UserServiceImpl(this.mockedUserRepository);
	User expected = this.testUser;
	
	
	// Act
	User actual = userService.getUserByUsername("Pesho");

	
	// Assert
	Assert.assertEquals("Broken...", expected.getId(), actual.getId());
	Assert.assertEquals("Broken...", expected.getUsername(), actual.getUsernam());
	Assert.assertEquals("Broken...", expected.getPassword(), actual.getPassword());
	}
}
=========================================================================================




Some of the most common levels of Software Testing

	- Unit Testing

		- Tests Individiual components of code, independent from the infrastructure

	- Component Testing

		- Testing of multiple functionalities (a single component)

	- Integration Testing

		- Testing of all integratedmodulesto verify the combined functionality

	- System Testing

		- Tests the systemas a whole, once all the components are integrated

	- Regression Testing

		- Ensures that a fixed bug won't happen again

	- Acceptance Testing

		- Tests if the productmeets the client’s requirements. Purely done by QAs

	- Load / Stress Testing 

		- Test the application’s limits by attempting large data processing 
			and introducting abnormal circumstances and conditions(edge cases)

	- Security Testing

		- Test if the application has any security flawsand vulnerabilities

	- Other Types of Testing

		- Manual, automation, UI, performance, black box, end-to-end testing, etc.
