Data Aggregation - how to get data insights


Grouping - Consulidating data based on criteria 

	- Grouping allows taking data into separate groups based on common property

	- With GROUP BY you can get each separate group and use an "aggregate"

		function over it (like Average, Min, Max, Sum)

		- Select e.`job_title`, COUNT(`employee_id`)
		  FROM `employees` AS e
		  GROUP BY e.`job_title`;


Aggregate Functions

	- Used to operate over one or more groups performing data analysis on every one

		- MIN, MAX, SUM, AVG, COUNT etc - SUM(`column_name`) 

		- They usually ignore NULL values

			- SELECT e.`department_id`, MIN (e.`salary`) AS 'MinSalary'
			  FROM `emplayees` AS e		
			  GROUP BY e.`department_id`;


HAVING - using predicate while grouping

	- The HAVING clause is used to filter data based on aggregate values

		- We cannont use it without grouping befero that

	- Any Aggregate functions in the HAVING clause and in the SELECT statement are executed one time only
	- Unlike HAVING, the WHERE clause filters rows before the aggregation

	- SELECT e.`department_id` SUM (e.`salary`) AS 'Total Salary'
	  FROM `employees` AS e
	  GROUP BY e.`department_id`
	  HAVING `Total	Salary` < 25 000; 