JOINS, Subqueries and Indices

JOINS - Gathering Data From Multiple Tables

	- JOINS used to collect data from two or more tables
	
	- Cartesian Product

		SELECT `last_name`, `name` AS `department_name`
		FROM employees, departments;

		- Each row in the first table is paired with all the rows in the second table

		- Formed when a JOIN condition is omitted/invalid

INNER JOIN

	- Produces a set of records which match in both tables
		
		SELECT student.name, courses.name
		FROM students
		INNER JOIN courses
		ON students.course_id = course.id;

LEFT JOIN 

	- Matches every entry in left table regardless of match in the right

		LEFT JOIN second_table_name

RIGHT JOIN 

	- Matches every entry in right table regardless of match in the left

		RIGHT JOIN second_table_name

OUTER(FULL JOIN)

	- Return all records in both tables regardless of any match 

		- Not implement in MySQL, we use UNION of a LEFT and RIGHT

UNION
			... LEFT JOIN query...
				UNION
			... Right JOIN query...

CROSS JOIN 

	- Produces a set of associated rows of two tables

		- Multiplocations of each row in the first table with each in second 

		- Result is Cartesian product, when there'no conditions in the WHERE clause

		- SELECT * FROM courses AS c
		  CROSS JOIN students As s;


Subqueries

	- SQL query inside a larger one, can be nested in SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE

INdices - Clustered and Non-Clustered Indices

	- CREATE INDEX
    	  	ix_users_first_name_last_name
		ON users(first_name, last_name);